so this is the
sub asava sabasa
nikaya ii
just a few sections that i want to speak
about
in the first section the basic summary
of it
says because i say that the destruction
of the taints
is for one who knows and sees not for
one who does not
does not know and see
and who knows and sees what
and it says yeah it's translated as wise
attention and unwise attention so he he knows the
and unwise attention so he he knows the
difference there
he knows okay so and that wise attention
is yoni so manisikara
and for now
i will translate that as an attention
with perspective
so who knows and sees what
you could probably say
perspective of attention so you know
perspective of attention and
non-perspective of attention exactly
so it's not the attention necessarily
that it's different
it's where your perspective on your
attention you don't have perspective
whether you're aware as we say
peripherally regarding what you're attending in front
regarding what you're attending in front
of you or you're not aware peripherally
of you
because that's exactly that's that's by
definition that's what perspective is
having perspective means not being
absorbed in like one
narrow one-pointed thing but actually
having perspective on it not losing the
context of that of that thing in that situation
of that of that thing in that situation
and you see why that's necessary because
often in the sutures we would give those
similes of
the trap the poison drink all that and
all those things can only be known if
you gain perspective in regard to it
because nothing you attend in the trap
will reveal the trap
as a trap that's why it's a trap but if
you know
if you have perspective that it's a trap
then you will basically not engage with
it if you have perspective that it
contains poison that you cannot detect
but you know
so there is perspective in regard to
attending to this poisonous drink
and you will not drink it that's what i
said there is no single thing
they would bring sensuality engaging
with your senses to diminish
as uh proper attention as perspective of
attention the only sumonasicara
and there is not a single thing that
would make sensuality to increase as
not having the perspective yeah ioniz
so you can
being lustful towards a
central image perspective in regard to
that would be well all the effort that you
would be well all the effort that you
put in practice in the demo that then
has revealed
um the sense objects to be perilous
dangerous resulting in death suffering so it's not
resulting in death suffering so it's not
something you always have to
i have to reattend now oh it's perilous
no it becomes part of the perspective
if you've been doing it rightly so every
time you attend to sensuality
as the buddha would say the danger is
apparent so you but when perspective becomes
so you but when perspective becomes
apparent means your yoni somanasikara
has been properly fulfilled
you're gaining knowledge and and wisdom
you have the bigger picture
yeah so it takes effort to be focusing
on the perspective or to like be
discerning the perspective while the
focus is taken by sensuality by
attention here and there but if you
invested enough of that peripheral
effort peripheral development
so to speak then things become apparent
so now when i attend to sensual
sensuality all i see is the danger now
if i attend to non-sensuality all always
sees peace and and
pleasure a pleasure renunciation but
that takes
takes effort to develop
but you have a perspective on what you
are attracted to
which undermines that attraction you're
craving so if you
you're attracted to another body a
female body
by having perspective on what the body
is sure
the perspective of the nature of the
body and and that's what i mean you want
to see it
those things on the level of perspective
not make another thing you're attending
off because either way you're unaware of
because either way you're unaware of
perspective that's how people do the
asuba wrongly
oh i see beautiful i must see ugly now i
must see ugly now but
that will work initially maybe when kind
of the reality that the
surreal kind of aspect of ugly hits you
but you get used to it
it ceases to be surreal either way you
haven't developed perspective so that's
when in the vienna particular like all those
in the vienna particular like all those
rules that revolve around like basically
people being attracted to
becoming attracted to ugly and breaking
rules and so on
because they haven't had perspective to
begin with so if you want to practice a
subarrightly it's in regard to the beautiful you want
it's in regard to the beautiful you want
to see the perspective as revealing the
ugly underneath
not make another thing you look at and
with your attention and stare at because
either way there will be no perspective
because if you look in the world there's
people who are attracted to
even the most disgusting yes even
excrement is attractive
yeah no there are exactly because it's
all because there's no perspective
so so no matter how whatever is in front
of you
has potential of becoming attractive
because you haven't uprooted sensuality
craving for pleasure and you are not
developing perspective
so just have it long enough sufficiently
enough and you'll be attracted to it
but if you do have perspective even the
most beautiful and attractive
things will actually be seen as ugly
because they are truly ugly
and and repulsive
if they weren't so sensuality would not
be unwholesome sensuality will not be a
contradiction it would not be pain it would not be a
it would not be pain it would not be a
cover-up it will not be basically
something you
you could get rid of
so when one
attends with a perspective
anarism taints arise
without without so when one attempts
without a perspective
unarisen taints arise and arisen tanks
increase when one attends with a perspective or
when one attends with a perspective or
has
one has perspective on one's attention
what one is tending to unrisen chains do
not arise and the risen taints are
abandoned that's what you
just said yeah i think what i was
thinking of was i think it was that it
was but he says the same it says the same
then that's that's the whole point like
you realize
it's it's the it's the it's the
fundamental it's like
right from the start whether you're
going to be going in the right direction
or the wrong direction
with perspective is the right direction
without perspective the wrong direction
so if you
if you start without a perspective on
the right level no amount of your
practice then
can sort of uh change the fact that you
took the first step in the wrong
direction and now that's where you're
hidden so that's why you'll be meditating with
so that's why you'll be meditating with
sensuality not free from sensuality not
really getting any any any distinction of of
getting any any any distinction of of
the of the kind that matters
so and that's why you only summon cigar
is one of the
prerequisites for becoming a sort of
runner so it's a necessary basis
if a platoon would have been like
obviously its
perspective is not a static thing some
people have more some people have less
of it some people are wiser naturally
some people are not because they
you know the life made them so they made
the effort whatever but fundamentally
you need more of a perspective it
doesn't matter how
lofty elevated protruding you are or not
you need more perspective
perspective on the certain universal
truths universal reality of things which
is what dharma is
so that means in other words some people
have little dust in their eyes some
people have more dust in their eyes
either way there is dust in their eyes
that needs to be removed
you can't have two you can't have too
much of the right perspective
exactly dharma is actually uprooting all
of your petunias perspectives
because if they were not wrong you would
be free from suffering
you would not need to practice
so that's why even as a prerequisite
yoni somanasigara needs to be developed
you don't have it and that's why often
like i i find it quite unfortunate it's often
i i find it quite unfortunate it's often
translated and watered
down you only say oh it's it's a wise
considering it's appropriate attention and so that's
it's appropriate attention and so that's
all stuff that putujna can relate to in
a sense of
oh yeah i wisely consider inappropriate
and and appropriately sort of approach
my sensuality
no if you are able to approach
centrality means there is no ionization but the eye
means there is no ionization but the eye
only so is there
yeah so basically then your idea of the
right perspective is fully
enveloped within the wrong perspective
so actually everyone has a perspective
there's always some perspective it's
just whether it's going to be
wrong or right whether it's going to be
limited or
or immeasurable depending on and certain
direction like
a limited perspective cannot result in
immeasurable perspective
but if you were to start developing the
direction of immeasurable perspective
that can result
in such perspectives but that
perspective takes cultivation and
development doesn't happen to you cannot happen it's
doesn't happen to you cannot happen it's
something you
you discern on an account of basically
being instructed so
joni summons and the right instruction
are the necessary two
prerequisites for a rising of the right
view so you need the right instruction but
so you need the right instruction but
you also need to have the right
perspective so putusina can engage in the right
so putusina can engage in the right
perspective
he can start doing it so to speak
and with the right instruction he'll
cease to be a patient
so right perspective is what this
described before looking at
the universal characteristics of your
current experience
and not letting yourself be pulled or
absorbed into the particulars
of your observations attention
techniques sense objects and so on that's the
sense objects and so on that's the
beginning of the
well that's at least the direction where
you will develop the right perspective
so obviously the right perspective of
anagami yoni sumanasi karavanagam is far
superior to the possibility of the only son is
to the possibility of the only son is
but it's the same direction so if the
starts developing it
he will free himself from sensuality for
example
so it's it's it's there it's the
crossroads so left or right
so to speak or more actually more
accurately it's more like
the two planes one is that the
horizontal plane of left right
front and back and the only summoning
cigar is the perpendicular plane
they would basically be surmounting any
direction you take with your attention
perspective is there unchanged
right it's about
pretty much like the nature of saturday
and mindfulness
which is also why you can't have too
much mindfulness right here it's pretty
much the same thing
so let's go to the next section and it
says it taints to be abandoned by
scene because here
because an untaught ordinary person
petuna who has no regard for the noble
ones and is unskilled and undisciplined in
and is unskilled and undisciplined in
their dhamma
who has no regard for true men and is
unskilled and undisciplined in the
dharma does not understand what things
are fit for attention and what things
are unfit for attention
since that is so he attends to things
unfit for attention
it does not attention things fit or
attention so he doesn't understand
what things if attended to
will obscure the perspective and what
things he's attended to will
fortify the perspective because he has
no perspective because he has no
perspective so it's a vicious circle
he's he's locked in
so that's why he needs to start
restraining beforehand out of faith
even if he has no recognition of the
value of sense restraint
and celebrity and so on he needs to
start doing it because
see at least he unknowingly he's
he's not fueling the wrong perspective
anymore so there is a possibility that
he's going to start seeing
things in the right right context and if
he met
the true men and success the noble ones
they would tell him just
that they would tell him you don't see
things correctly but
do this start restraining yeah so yeah
that is the parallel situation of potus
you said many times before
you don't know the escape you don't see
the truth
the right order the right perspective
and because of that
the lack of perspective is getting worse
you think you have the right
so there has to be a perspective there
but it's just going to be wrong and more
wrong
because what are things unfit for
attention that he attends to
there are things such when he attends
them the aneurysm
taint of central the desire arises
and the risen taint of central desire
increases and the taint of being in the taint of
and the taint of being in the taint of
ignorance
yeah we said that in other talks he
connects the same way we talk about
the meditation and how to how basically
most people's meditation revolves around
saying still about paramount the virtual
duty the fatter
the first factor that that impedes them
it's it's it's related exactly to that
so
by not knowing by not having perspective
or what you need to do what you need to
attend to
you tend to write things wrongly wrong
things rightly
wrong things wrongly but you kind of
think to write things rightly
because you have no perspective on it
and then
and that's what happens when when people
without such perspective then
uh take on the practice and so on but
practice is not it's not instructing them and
is not it's not instructing them and
teaching them how to look
basically and develop perspective in
regard to what they're practicing
is just making them go through the
motions of their practice or keep the
precepts and then do this and then do
this and then do this and then here's
your mantra and then do this
and the more they do it the less the
further away from getting the direction
the right perspective they are
so you you have to do something and the
buddha says what you do
sense restraint virtue
well controlling your senses and so on
so that's what you're doing and yeah
that is a factor to begin with even if
somebody's doing it rightly
but now you're also instructed to look
at them to gain perspective
in regard to what you're doing now just
do this
do this and then understand why you're
doing what you're doing
so you you can't stop doing it so you
can't stop keeping the precepts in order
to understand
why you're keeping the presets you have
to keep keeping the precepts in order to
be able to understand
eventually the purpose of keeping the
precepts and then you won't be keeping
them in that sense you won't be having to
in that sense you won't be having to
attend to them and do them because now
you understood
their place and their nature and same
you wouldn't be then doing any more
meditation methods and techniques
because that was done before with there
was no perspective you were hoping of
going through the motions will somehow
bestow the knowledge upon you but now no
it's me gaining knowledge in regard to
what i'm doing
in regard to keeping the precepts in
regard to sensory strain yeah in regard
to sitting quietly
just keeping the gaze in front of myself
not being distracted
but i'm not doing it as a method or a
technique that i will adhere to
for four minutes 30 seconds i'm doing it
so i can understand
like the perspective behind the
universal characteristics of that
withdrawal composure mindfulness all
these things and that's how
understanding can arise
and that's how you would overcome the
first factor of doing
things on account of practice and not
seeing how they would be supporting the
how they would be supporting the
practice
they have no direct knowledge of that so
you just take on faith that being
restrained and so on will help my
practice you take on faith that if i keep trying
you take on faith that if i keep trying
to meditate i will get the right
meditation
but unless your meditation your
priesthood are being reflected upon and
you're trying to understand them as to
why is this wholesome why is this world of
is this wholesome why is this world of
development why is this
why would this result in freedom from
suffering you will never understand it
because no amount of do this do this and
keep these precepts would would result
in dharma arising you
that's what they said themselves said
that when they were
at the first council well what should we
recite first the
the vinaya the rules or the suta well
the suit is the dharma
but they said but there's no damage
there's no doubt without the rules
so rules are not the dhamma but there is
no dharma without the basis of rules
so let's recite the rules first so they
recited all the stories from the
winnipetica and then went into dhamma so rules are
and then went into dhamma so rules are
not the dharma
but you wouldn't be able to have any
dumb whatsoever if there are no rules
established and when i say rules i mean virtue
and when i say rules i mean virtue
presets
and and sense restraint because it's all
about that
it's like a calming form yeah so it's
like you you should you could ask
yourself as somebody who wants to praise
them and keep us a precept you ask
yourself okay so do i understand
this relationship between dharma and the
precepts or do i think that my keeping with the
or do i think that my keeping with the
precepts equates
practicing of the dharma because it
doesn't actually
keeping the preset is one thing
practicing dhamma is the other
so oh do i understand this no if you
don't understand it if you don't see
clearly you are taking the precepts they are
you are taking the precepts they are
factoring you and yeah see about the
bottom us
virtue duty the good things the
wholesome thing
are fetter because you have no
perspective are you honest you're attending them
are you honest you're attending them
without perspective
and even if a hundred years so it's good
in terms of making merit being virtuous
and sensory strained but there will be
no wisdom arising
so even if you're for 100 years you just
keep the rules but never
invest effort into developing that
perpendicular direction of
oh what's the what's the context of this
rules that i will not break
but let me understand this the purpose
and when you do then you don't need to
hold it the knowledge has taken place
and as we said like a noble person is
free from that fatter
of silabata paramasa even if they would
sometimes due to circumstances
break the rules all they would need to
do is just recognize that
and and immediately pretty much their
practice would be restored when they see
fault as fault because they see fault is
fault they will understand it while
somebody who is not
free from paramasa when they break the
rules it's even worse because they had no
it's even worse because they had no
perspective even with the rules
so they can't just repair it with an
insight back on
because they had no insight to begin
with so that's why you have to
develop that actually seeing the danger
in the slightest fault because yeah the
slightest fault
can undermine everything you build up
that could have possibly helped you gain
perspective on your own keeping the precepts for
on your own keeping the precepts for
example
and we spoke about it in other talks
like you realize in the beginning you
keep the precepts
if you gain the perspective it's not
about me
doing the presets it's simply me not
doing anything
against the precepts so you don't need
to keep the precepts all you need to do
is not break them
and then they're there because that
became your mode of behavior
that's why there were no rules in the
beginning that was obvious that people
understood the dhamma
and that's why that when that monk asked
the buddha uh
there were too many 100 something rules
at the time he said it's too many for me
to keep i can't
wrap my head around it and he said can
you keep what three
don't do anything rooted in greed
aversion and distraction
yeah don't do anything enhancing it
cultivate the whole
don't do anything on wholesome voting
and hold some sort of giving the rules
so
yeah even just two rules so he wouldn't
he knew oh
anything that i can recognize because he
had perspective as an also i'll not do
it even if there is no specific letter
of the rule that bans you from doing it
you know that it's bad because it's
rooted in three diversion delusion and
you won't do it and if that's your
criteria you can never break the rules because
you can never break the rules because
yeah you can take it even on that
fundamental level so there is no rule
against i don't know talking to
to people something awesome
but you recognize that your motivation
for doing so
is rooted and you want to be distracted
or or
whatever entertained
lustful for whatever reason you're
engaging in that which is not
unwholesome in its letter but it's
unwholesome and you would have perspective on that
and you would have perspective on that
because your fundamental motivation
is the fundamental perspective of your
action and that's what i said every action is
and that's what i said every action is
intention
it's rooted in your intention that
determines the action
even if like publicly like you know from
the third person point of view
it is nothing on wholesome they're
talking about books
and suttas antipatica but he does that
internally for unwholesome reasons
or for not so wholesome reasons so if
your criteria now
which your right perspective is to never
do things that are rooted in greed
aversion distraction
you can never basically be a wholesome
you can never break the rules
because you're not guided now by the
letter oh but the rule says i can talk
to people
yeah that doesn't matter that's like a
very uh base criteria for people that
have no criteria at all
but you should strive higher than that
if you were to develop yoni summoners
got it properly
you would have perspective that
wholesome unwholesome is determined by
wholesome and wholesome
intention behind those actions and
that's the criteria you follow even if
there is no
formulated rule against it so that's if
you start practicing like that there are
no loopholes
in vinaya because it's all either rooted
in wholesale and wholesome or neutral
so john is pretty much the
the fundamental thread that can take you
from putin estate
to being fully enlightened if you
cultivate it
and i think we mentioned it before it's
like becoming that you know concern for
your own welfare
and then recognizing the the necessity
of accepting responsibility
for your actions for your senses for for
your intentions for everything
because when you're responsible or when
you feel responsible
well you cannot afford to lose
perspective or this is really important
i will consider everything before i
commit to it only when you are
irresponsible you just act out even even in mundane
you just act out even even in mundane
terms even in colloquial sense
irresponsible people are people that
don't really consider things they don't
really have context they don't have perspective
have context they don't have perspective
they just want this don't want this they
just irresponsibly act and then pretend
it never happened or whatever else
so accepting responsibility for your own
situation even things you're not in
control of so to speak it's it's better
because it can then prompt you in the
direction of developing right
perspective in the right context which
is
pretty much the beginning of your
honesty and then with the right
instruction you can get the right view on account of
you can get the right view on account of
it so
if you wonder how it would feel like to
do that well
ask yourself even in mundane terms is
responsibility pleasant or unpleasant
is responsibility burden or
light-hearted joy
oh no it's so it's going to be heavier
in the beginning more unpleasant
because most of the life is about
avoiding responsibility and getting the
pleasure that covers up any any sense of burden
that covers up any any sense of burden
but if you realize that that's not
optional and you start accepting that
burden of responsibility
as a petunia that's that that's the
basically precaution to the yoni
sumanasika that and you know the mundane right view
that and you know the mundane right view
oh there
there are the results of my action there
is you know there is given there is way
there is significance of things
i cannot just ignore there is the fact
that i don't know
that's also the truth for you to begin
with that i'm not liberated i'm not free
from suffering
i don't have that why is perspective
exactly so accepting the reality of your
situation and responsibility for you
being in it
because you keep yourself in whatever
perspective you are in
right or wrong by cultivating wrong
perspective that's what's going to
proliferate and diversify and become
more by abstaining from it and kind of going
by abstaining from it and kind of going
against the pull of the
wrong perspective and trying to develop
that perpendicular right perspective
that will be on you again through your
own effort you can
so either way you need to take responsibility